Preliminary Inventory of the United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of Government Records
Hoover Institution Archives
United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of Government records,
1947-1955
XX312
United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1947-1949)
36 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box 15.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, minutes, press releases, and printed matter, relating to rationalization of the organization of the executive branch of the United States government. Includes records of the second Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1953-1955).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Historical Note
The First Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, chaired by former President Herbert Hoover, was established by act of July 7, 1947 (61 Stat. 246). The commission studied and investigated the organization and methods of operation of the Executive branch of the federal government, and recommended organization changes to promote economy, efficiency, and improved service. Operating through functional area task forces, it submitted numerous full commission and individual task force reports to Congress. The final report, published as Concluding Report: Report to Congress, May 1949, included an index to previously submitted reports. The commission was terminated June 12, 1949, as provided in the enabling legislation.
The Second Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, chaired by former President Herbert Hoover, was established by act of July 10, 1953 (67 Stat. 142), and extended by act of May 23, 1955 (69 Stat. 64). It studied and investigated organization and methods of operation of the Executive branch of the federal government, and recommended organization changes to promote economy, efficiency, and improved service. The commission's final report to Congress was submitted on June 29, 1955, and was published in two volumes as Final Report to the Congress and Index to the Commission and Task Force Reports, June 1955. The commission was terminated June 30, 1955, as provided in extending legislation, with an additional ninety days for liquidation.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, reports, minutes, press releases, and printed matter, relating to rationalization of the organization of the executive branch of the United States government. Includes records of the second Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1953-1955).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
United States--Politics and government.; United States--Executive departments.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1953-1955)
Contents
- First Hoover Commission reports, task force reports, published and unpublished (Box 1-12)
- Press releases (Box 13-16)
- Key personnel
- Acknowledgments - Letters
- Minutes of meeting
- Digest of reports
- Fan mail - First Commission
- Second Hoover Commission reports (Box 17-19)
- (2) Digests
- Public law
- Press releases (Box 20-23)
- Minutes of meetings
- Bills - Second Commission
- Management handbook
- Reports - Unpublished - Mimeographed
- Medical reports - Staff papers
- Legal service - Staff papers
- Procurement - Staff papers
- Report of the Subcommittee on Transportation, to the Committee on Business Organization for the Department of Defense and the Subsistence Services Task Force, 1954 November 30 (Box 24)
  - Volume 1: "Government Traffic Management and Transportation"
  - Volume 2: "Military Sea Transportation Service, Military Air Transportation Service, Panama Railroad and Panama Line"
- Report of the Committee on Business Organization of the Department of Defense: "Programs for Improving Management," 1955 May
- Report of Price Waterhouse and Company: "Summary of the Government's Lending and Related Insurance and Guarantee Activities." Copy No. 40
- Report of the Task Force on Subsistence Services, 1955 February (Box 25)
  - Volume I: Food Section
  - Volume II: Clothing Section
  - Volume III: Competition with Private Enterprise
  - Volume IV: Fiscal Controls
- Report of the Task Force on Legal Services and Procedure, 1954 December 31
  - Volume IV: Legal Representation
  - Volume V: Legislative and Administrative Implementation of Recommendations
- Task Force Report: "Evaluation, Analysis and Recommendations on the Government's Lending and Related Insurance and Guarantee Activities." Copy No. 31 (Box 26)
- Report of the Task Force on Federal Real Property, 1955 April 29
- Report of the Task Force on Military Procurement, 1955 May
- Report of the Task Force on Paperwork Management in the U.S. Government, 1954 November 18
- Report of the Task Force on Legal Services and Procedure, 1954 December 31 (Box 27)
  - Volume I: General Report and Recommendation
  - Volume II: Legal Services
  - Volume III: Legal Procedures, Parts 1 and 2
- Reports to the Task Force on Water Resources and Power (Box 28)
  - Clarenbach, Fred A., professor of political science, University of Wisconsin: "Reliability of Estimates of Agricultural Damages from Floods," 1954 October 21
  - Curran, Charles D., task force administrator
    - "Application of the Interest Component of Power Revenue from Reclamation Project under the Solicitor's Opinion and the Collbran Formula," 1954 October 4
    - "Evaluation of Federal Navigation Projects," 1955 March 4
  - Frederick, John H., professor of transportation, University of Maryland: "User Charges on the Waterways of the United States," 1954 October 5
  - Hoyt, William G., staff consultant: "Competition for the Use of Water," 1954 November 5
  - Hoyt, William G., and Walter B. Langbein: "Flood Management through Zoning - Insurance and Forecasting," 1954 October 21
  - Huffman, Roy E., professor and head, Department of Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology, Montana State College: "The Reclamation of Land for Agricultural Purposes," 1954 November 12
  - Krause, Keith S., sanitary engineer
    - "The Federal Government and Water Pollution Control," 1954 August 13
    - "The Relationship of Federal Activities to Municipal and Industrial Water Supply," 1954 August 23
  - O'Brien, John B., Jr., legal advisor
    - "Federal Water Law, 1950-54," 1954 November 22
    - "The Preference Clause in Federal Electric Development and Distribution - Its History, Intent and Impact," 1955 February 10
  - Page, Norvell W., staff consultant: "Patterns of Federal-Nonfederal Partnership in Water Resource Development," 1954 October 6
  - Peltier, Richard J., staff editorial assistant: "Federal Gathering of Basic Water Resource Facts," 1955 February 24
  - Sturm, Alber L, professor of political science, West Virginia University: "Civil Functions of the Corps of Engineers Relation to Military Mission," 1954 October 30
  - Task Group on Reclamation and Water Supply: L. A. Miller, chairman; J. Hinds; H. E. Polk; R. J. Tipton; 1955 March 31
  - Task Group on Flood Control: W. W. Horner, chairman; W. B. Bates; H. W. Morrison; F. H. Newman, Jr.; 1955 March 31
  - Taylor, Perry R., government organization analyst: "Inventory of the Federal Agencies Handling Water Resources and Power Development and Conservation," 1954 October 15
  - Vawter, Wallace R., senior specialist in engineering and public works
    - "Case Study of the Arkansas-White-Red Basin Inter-Agency Committee," 1954 July 8
    - "Interstate Compacts - The Federal Interest," 1954 March 16
  - Various maps
- Public Hearings of the Task Force on Water Resources and Power (Box 29)
  - Transcripts of proceedings
    - New York, New York
      - Volume 1: Morning session, 1954 June 14
      - Volume 2: Afternoon session, 1954 June 14
      - Volume 3: Morning session, 1954 June 15
      - Volume 4: Afternoon session, 1954 June 15
    - Chattanooga, Tennessee (Box 30)
      - Volume 1: Morning session, 1954 June 1
      - Volume 2: Afternoon session, 1954 June 1
      - Volume 3: Morning session, 1954 June 2
      - Volume 4: Afternoon session, 1954 June 2
    - Portland, Oregon (Box 31)
      - Volume 1: Morning session, 1954 June 28
      - Volume 2: Afternoon session, 1954 June 28
      - Volume 1: Morning session, 1954 June 29
      - Volume 2: Afternoon session, 1954 June 29
    - Denver, Colorado (Box 32)
      - Volume 1: Morning session, 1954 May 17
      - Volume 2: Afternoon session, 1954 May 17
      - Volume 3: 1954 May 18
  - Digest of written statements and of transcript of answer to questions
    - San Francisco, California, 1954 May 3-4
    - Chattanooga, Tennessee, 1954 June 1-2
- Miscellany (Box 33)
  - Diary
    - Letters, memoranda, press releases, report drafts
      - 1953 September - 1954 February
      - 1954 March - 1954 July (Box 34)
      - 1954 August - 1955 June (Box 35)
  - Letters, papers, articles, n.d. (Box 36)